MICHAEL NSIAH-NIMO, M.Sc.

DATA SCIENCE | ANALYTICS

CONTACT

GitHub

michael20129648@gmail.com

in <u>Linkedin</u>

Project Portfolio

SKILLS & TOOLS

- Programming: Python (Base, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Scikit-Learn, Keras, TensoFlow), SQL, R, SAS
- Machine Learning: Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, Random Forest, KNN, k-means, PCA, Association Rule Learning, Causal Impact Analysis, Deep Learning, NLP, Generative AI and LLMs
- Statistics: Experimental Design,
 Multivariate Analysis, Study Design
 and Sample Size Estimation,
 Statistical Modeling, Parametric and
 Non Parametric Statistics , Multilevel
 Modeling, Survival Analysis,
 Longitudinal Data Analysis,
 Hypothesis Generation and Testing,
 Randomization and Clinical Trials,
 Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)
 Creation , Data Mining and
 Visualization, Report Generation and
 Interpretation
- Professional Skills: Statistics, Github, Data Visualization, MS Office, Tableau, Jupyter Notebook, AWS, Google Cloud Platform

EDUCATION

MSc Statistics

University of Texas at El Paso

2015 - 2017

BSc Actuarial Science

Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology

2010 - 2014

PROFILE

I am driven by a deep passion for addressing business challenges through Data Science, Statistics, and Machine Learning. With over 6 years of experience, I apply my skills systematically and creatively to deliver tangible value to teams, businesses, and end-users. I maintain a continuous learning mindset, constantly seeking ways to enhance my expertise and make meaningful contributions.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist and Research Analyst

University of Texas at El Paso, College of Science, Research Enterprise

JULY 2020 - PRESENT

- Led a team of 5 data scientists to develop a Python-based Deep Learning model for a 5 year national grant award to predict the biological age of Hispanic Origin Individuals (HOI) using proteomics data on inflammatory cytokines, chemokines, and growth factors. The model's output provided participants with an estimated biological age a proxy of the inflammatory burden of the individual, enabling them to compare it with their chronological age and make informed decisions about their health and nutrition habits.
- Utilized seaborn visualization and regression models in Python statsmodels
 package to analyze the relationships between estimated biological ages, sociobehavioral factors, and health determinants in individuals of Hispanic Origin.
 This analysis identified crucial features for our predictive model, supporting a
 federal grant application and subsequent analytics. Ultimately, our approach led
 to a 30% cost reduction in measuring social factors, optimizing resource
 utilization for comprehensive investigations.
- Pioneered and Spearheaded the implementation of advanced Big Data
 methodologies at the UTEP Center for Integrative and Translational Research
 (CITR) with the Dean of Research to foster collaboration and innovation among
 interdisciplinary researchers. Through the Analytics Core, we established a
 comprehensive data repository to address health disparities for Mexican-origin
 Hispanics by integrating diverse determinants of health. This led to and
 advanced and continuous improvement in healthcare equity which underscored
 tremendous transformative initiatives aimed at positively impacting underserved
 communities.

Data Analyst

College of Science, University of Texas at El Paso

JUNE 2018 - JULY 2020

- Used SQL, Tableau, and MapBox to extract and model demographic data from El Paso County and created dynamic visualization reports which uplifted more targeted grant applications for health disparities research in the College of Science by 50%
- Originated and analyzed comprehensive social determinants of health trends to identify prevalent issues related to obesity, cancer and metabolic syndrome in the Borderplex region with the Assistant Dean of Research and Leadership.
- Lead a team of scholars and analysts to mined, explore and analyze several
 data sources including electronic health records, biosamples, surveys, physical
 measurements and wearable devices, utilizing the NIH All of Us Data Repository
 to secure federal grants from the National Institute of Health (NIH) and
 foundation grants from organizations like the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation
 and the Bill Gates Foundation. I supervised and contributed to critical research
 initiatives focused on health disparities, clinical research, and socio-behavioral
 research
- Presented and participated in cutting edge data science and statistical
 conferences and seminars to improve knowledge in bioinformatics, data
 science, and health equity, in the College of Sciences to drive impactful research
 outcomes.

MICHAEL NSIAH-NIMO, M.Sc.

DATA SCIENCE | ANALYTICS

COURSES & CERTIFICATIONS

DSI Data Science Professional Certification Actionable Learnings:

- Extracting & manipulating data using SQL.
 Application of statistical concepts such as
 hypothesis tests for measuring the effect of
 AB Tests. Utilizing Github for version control,
 and collaboration. Using Python for data
 analysis, manipulation & visualization
- Applying data preparation steps for ML including missing values, categorical variable encoding, outliers, feature scaling, feature selection & model validation
- Applying Machine Learning algorithms for regression, classification, clustering, association rule learning, and causal impact analysis for measuring the impact of an event over time.
- Machine Learning pipelines to streamline the ML pre-processing & modelling phase.
 Deployment of a ML pipeline onto a live website using Streamlit.
- Using Tableau to create powerful Data Visualizations. Turning business problems into Data Science solutions.

Machine Learning Specialization (Deep Learning.ai - Coursera) Actionable Learnings:

- Built machine learning models in Python using popular machine learning libraries NumPy and scikitlearn. Built and trained supervised machine learning models for prediction and binary classification tasks, including linear regression and logistic regression.
- Built and trained a neural network with TensorFlow to perform multi-class classification. Applied the best practices for machine learning development so that the models generalized to data and tasks in the real world

Conferences Attended

- Cardwell Foundation Seminar, 2016
- College of Science Stakeholders', 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022
- University of Hawaii Bioinformatics Data Science Workshops, 2023
- NIH NIGMS Cloud Based Biomedical Research, 2023
- Better Data for More Equitable Research : Research America Alliance, 2023
- RCMI Seminars at Meharry Medical College, 2023
- Microsoft Al Research Forum, 2024
- JSM Conference 2017, Diversity Scholar

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Analyst

Uinversity of Texas at El Paso, Center for Institutional, Research and Planning

SUMMER 2018

- Served as a lead statistician in project planning. design, and analysis, identifying research designs and pertinent data: to address institutional and educational policy issues at UTEP.
- Retrieval and mined higher educational research databases, which generated reports focused on institutional research and continuous improvement.
- Contributed to the development of academic publications and presentations showcasing the utilization of Big Data for institutional research, which facilitated informed decision-making among university stakeholders.

Projects

Enhancing Targeting Accuracy Using ML

Built a ML model that accurately predicted whether or not customers would sign
up for a delivery club. This allowed a critical targeted approach essential to
comprehending and running the next iteration of the campaign.

Predicting Customer Loyalty Using ML

 Built a predictive model using a Random Forest in Python that estimated customer loyalty scores for customers that a company's data agency couldn't tag (r-squared 93%). This led to a 30% increase in customers we could analyze, and contact with promotional material.

Quantifying Sales Uplift With Causal Impact Analysis

Employed causal impact analysis to quantify the increase in sales attributed to
customers joining the company's delivery club compared to what they would
have spent without the club. The analysis revealed a significant 41.1% uplift in
sales among club members, indicating the club's positive impact on customer
spending.

"You Are What You Eat" Customer Segmentation

 Used k-means clustering on grocery transaction data to split out customers into distinct "shopper types" that could be used to better understand customers over time, and to target customers more accurately with relevant content & promotions.

Efficacy of Treatment Sessions in a Medical Emergency Department

Interaction Plots and Linear Mixed Models were developed and implemented to
provide appropriate services to individuals having problematic patterns and use
of illicit drugs (cocaine, cannabis). Hypotheses tests were conducted to
investigate if there were differences in means amongst different treatment
sessions as well as interactions between levels of age, sessions and gender.

Federal and Foundational Grants Projects

- National Institute of Health (NIH) U54's for the College's Research Core,.
- NIH All of Us Data for Preliminary Data for Health Disparities Research.
- NIH U54 Clinical Research.
- NIH U54 Socio behavioral Research.
- NIH Covid U54 Supplements.
- NIH C06 Grants for the Borderplex Biomedical Research Core.
- NIMHD Grants for Health Disparities, RCMI Grants for Hispanic Health Disparities
- Robert Wood Johnson Foundation Hispanic Health Disparities Grant
- Bill Gates Foundation Health Equity Grant.
- · Arnold Ventures Health Services Inequity and Disparities Grant
- Paso Del Norte Health Research Grants